<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The 14. of September. A relation of many memorable passages from Rome, Italy, Spaine, France, Germany, the Lovv-Countries, the Palatinate, and other places with some famous exploits performed at Bergen-Vpzom since the 4. of this moneth, stilo nouo.</title>
            <title>Relation of many memorable passages from Rome, Italy, Spaine, France, Germany, the Low-Countries, the Palatinate, and other places.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08165</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.77</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119974</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855178</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855178</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20653</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08165)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20653)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1186:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The 14. of September. A relation of many memorable passages from Rome, Italy, Spaine, France, Germany, the Lovv-Countries, the Palatinate, and other places with some famous exploits performed at Bergen-Vpzom since the 4. of this moneth, stilo nouo.</title>
                  <title>Relation of many memorable passages from Rome, Italy, Spaine, France, Germany, the Low-Countries, the Palatinate, and other places.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathaniel Butter, Barthol. Downes, and William Shefford,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Formerly STC 21295.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21295 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; last two leaves torn, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20653:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20653:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The 14. of September. A RELATION OF MANY MEMORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Paſſages from ROME, ITALY, SPAINE, FRANCE, GERMANY, the LOVV-COVNTRIES, the PALATINATE, and other Places:</p>
            <p>WITH Some Famous Exploits performed at <hi>BERGEN-VPZOM</hi> ſince the 4. of this Moneth, <hi>Stilo Nouo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter, Barthol. Downes,</hi> and <hi>William Shefford,</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="royal_blazon">
            <pb facs="tcp:20653:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20653:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENTS <hi>From Forraine Parts.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue (though later) ſent you the occurrents of Newes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers places; If they come not to your hands ſo ſoone as perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture you doe expect, impute it not to any neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence or want of good will towards you, but rather, for that I would firſt be poſſeſt truly of the truth of what I ſend you, which I can by no meanes be if I ſhall poſt you ouer Newes vpon the firſt report, which can neither be ſo true, nor ſo particular, and therefore vnleſſe I receiue writing (from each ſeuerall place, of each ſeuerall action) from men of the beſt credit, I will not offer it to your ſerious view, neither will I write you the ſame things which I writ you before as neere as I can; yet peraduenture ſome paſſages may be reported againe which the circumſtance of time may make different: So for preſent, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto you ſuch things as I haue receiued, by this Poſt, doe take leaue,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Don Hage,</hi> 
                  <date>this 6. of September, 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20653:3"/>
               <head>FROM VIENNA the eighteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1622.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Aſt Sunday, had the eldeſt ſonne of the late Marqueſſe <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardſten Fortunatus</hi> of <hi>Baden</hi> Audience of the Emperour, and ſolicited very earneſtly to bee enſtalled into the vpper Marqueſſat of <hi>Baden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Maieſty and the Empreſſe, with the young Prince and Princeſſe, were laſt Munday in the Ieſuites Colledge with great deuotion, where they receiued the holy Sacrament.</p>
               <p>His maieſtie cauſed his Priuie Councell to ſit yeſterday, where he himſelfe was preſent.</p>
               <p>This day they went all together with a ſtrong Conuoy to the Cloyſter <hi>Nieuborgh</hi> to hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Lichtenſtein,</hi> is lookt for heere daily to receiue the Order of the <hi>Golden-Fleece.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe here is lookt daily for certaine Commiſſioners, namely, the Lord <hi>Gondtacker</hi> of <hi>Lichtenſtein,</hi> the Lord <hi>Heghenmuller,</hi> the Lord Doctor <hi>Moſmuller,</hi> the Lord <hi>Iohn Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta Spindler</hi> of <hi>Egh,</hi> beſides the Lord <hi>George Mullner</hi> the Secretary of <hi>Lucts,</hi> which are to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20653:3"/>be ſent into the Countrey of <hi>Enns,</hi> to enquire in all places of the Rebels; And according to their offences to giue them iuſt Iudgement: What further will enſue time will reueale.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Spyer</hi> the 26. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe 21. of this Moneth the Enemy ſhot very fiercely vpon <hi>Heidelbergh,</hi> ſo that it was heard here very eaſily, but they within de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelues brauely. We alſo vndeſtand, that thoſe of <hi>Franckendall</hi> are reſolued to reſiſt and defend themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Wormes</hi> the 29. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CErtaine daies agoe the Arch-Duke <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pold</hi> went from hence againe, and left ſome of his Forces here, taking with him two Companies of the Townes Gariſons; his whole Armie lieth round about this City.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Crabats</hi> pilledge as far euen vnto <hi>Franc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kendall,</hi> all the ſouldiers which they light on there abouts, they put vnto the ſword. Our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens were forced to deliuer all their great Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-wood vnto them to make fagots of them, to fill vp the Towne-dirches withall, for the ſame Towne is giuen booty vnto the <hi>Crabats.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Hanaw</hi> the firſt of <hi>September.</hi> 1622.</head>
               <p>THe Enemies ſhot daily at <hi>Heidlebergh</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Schliebacher</hi> ſide, for the <hi>Bauarians</hi> haue taken in a Sconce beneath the Parke, which Count <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> did raiſe, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as yet they doe little hurt.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20653:4"/>
               <p>The Gariſon at <hi>Tilpergh</hi> did ſally forth not long ſince, and tooke thoſe Inſtruments and Engines, of the which the <hi>Bauarians</hi> would haue made a Bridge ouer the Riuer of <hi>Necker,</hi> and carried them into the Caſtle.</p>
               <p>Euen now there was brought from <hi>Stein</hi> to <hi>Laudenbourgh,</hi> ſome 30. ſmall Boats, whether they ſhall be vſed to the making of a Bridge or not, we doe not know.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leopoldus</hi> is come to <hi>Wormes</hi> againe, but his forces lie at <hi>Landan</hi> and thereabouts, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is reported, that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is to come vp againe, all the paſſages are ſtrongly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet againſt his ariuall here.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Franckfort</hi> the 2. of <hi>September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE haue certaine newes out of the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> that the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> is gone from <hi>Wormes</hi> towards <hi>Spire</hi> againe, but hath left ſome forces there for a certaine time, whoſe number encreaſeth dayly more and more, and the moſt part of his Army lyeth round about the ſame City, in the next Villages adioyning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto. It is ſuppoſed that <hi>Frankendale</hi> ſhall be ſet vpon, which Towne is reſolued to defend it ſelfe to the laſt man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heidlebergh</hi> is beſieged againe by the <hi>Bauari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as already is mentioned, and play very fiercely with their Ordnance vpon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:20653:4"/>
               <head>From <hi>Cullen</hi> the 3. of <hi>September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe laſt Sunday they began to ſhoot with two halfe Cannons on this ſide very hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vpon the Fort Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nmuts, but that did not continue long, for they within diſcharged their Ordnances from two of their Bulwarkes vpon the enemies batteries, and diſmounted both their halfe Cannons, one of them hauing the mouth of him ſhot away, the other burſt in the ſide. And the ſame battery by the meanes of the often ſhooting is ſo ruinated and ſpoyled, that it is thought the Country people will haue a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nights worke before they can repaire it againe.</p>
               <p>Few dayes agoe they of the Fort went abroad into the land of <hi>Berghen,</hi> from whence they tooke certaine Cattle, and carried them into the Sconſe with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Duſſeldorpe</hi> the 7. of <hi>September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere was carryed laſt thurſday from hence two pieces of Artillery more into the Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger before the Fort Papenmuts, they within as we vnderſtand haue great ſtore of prouiſion, and they practiſe dayly, yet in the like manner to prouide for themſelues hauing at this inſtant ſuch good opportunity, ſeeing the Sconſe before it vpon the cleue ſide is quite battered downe by them within.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20653:5"/>
               <head>From <hi>Dordrechtden</hi> the 3. of <hi>September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe 20. of Auguſt, in the euening, from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the clocke vntill three after mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, there was a great aſſault giuen before <hi>Berghen vp zome,</hi> wherein were ſlaine eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the enemies ſide, amongſt which were many great perſons, beſides ſixe hundred of them were hurt, and certaine of them taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners: of our ſide there was ſlaine 30. and 80. wounded, and the enemy was forced to forſake the halfe Moone, but kept the Liuie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spinola</hi> did write Letters vnto the Arch-dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe, the contents whereof was, that he muſt haue more forces to become Maſter of <hi>Bergen vp zome,</hi> entreating her Highneſſe to write to the aforeſaid Monſire <hi>Tilly,</hi> for certaine thouſand Souldiers to aſſiſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Gochdan</hi> the 2. of <hi>September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe 30. of Auguſt, Count <hi>Henry Vanden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> aroſe with his whole Campe before this Towne, with an intent to beate Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> with the helpe of <hi>Don Cordua,</hi> but when he perceiued that Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> were arriued with their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Brabant,</hi> he came the ſame day backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to <hi>Venlo,</hi> where he marched ouer the bridge and quartered his whole Army about ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſtrong at <hi>Venlo,</hi> and in certaine Villages thereabouts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20653:5"/>
               <head>From the Fort called <hi>Gravenweerdt,</hi> or <hi>Schen ckes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſconſe</hi> the 25. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> the olde ſtyle.</head>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> lyeth as yet here within the Fort, and his Campe on the other ſide the River <hi>Wael,</hi> in their old quarter. Certaine dayes agoe, when hee vnderſtood, that Count <hi>Henry Vanden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh,</hi> was determined to make himſelfe Maſter of the Towne <hi>Griet,</hi> he ſent in all haſte 2000. Muska<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers thither, and other neceſſaries belonging to the defence of the ſame Towne, and cauſed it to bee ſtrengthened round about. Likewiſe we vnderſtand that the aboue named Count was gone from the Towne <hi>Goch,</hi> taking his way towards <hi>Vente</hi> ouer the bridge, yet returnes backe againe, ſending certaine of his troopes towards our Campe, to try their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
               <p>Intending to make an aſſault vpon thoſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters where our horſe men lay, but this was betimes diſcovered by ſome of our forces, wherefore there roſe an Alarum in our leaguer, by reaſon whereof, the enemie ſaved themſelues by flight.</p>
               <p>From the Campe of his Excellency the twentie ſixe of Auguſt, there went from hence, Monſieur <hi>Marquet,</hi> with foure other perſons in a boate into <hi>Breda,</hi> where he is to ſtay, ſixe or ſeaven dayes, the reaſon whereof is as yet kept ſecret.</p>
               <p>Certaine daies agoe, there went out of our Campe, two thouſand Swimmers, but whether is not knowne, in regard they are not as yet returnd.</p>
               <p>The Prince hath ſent for certaine boates from <hi>Arnhem Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>umegen,</hi> and other places there-abouts (as we vnderſtand) to breake vp his Campe. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20653:6"/>wee heare that certaine ſouldiers the 25.26.27. in the night time tooke ſhipping, and that many Officers haue ſhipt their baggage alreadie.</p>
               <p>Wee haue certaine advertiſement that Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> are ſafely arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at <hi>Tilborgh</hi> about <hi>Breda,</hi> where dayly comes more and more vnto them, which by the meanes of their wearines could not follow, ſo that it is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped within few dayes their Campe will bee by the fourth part ſtrengthened, what enterpriſe they will afterward attempt, time will diſcloſe.</p>
               <p>This weeke and the next all the Directors and Aſſiſtants for the Weſt Indian Companie, ſhall be choſen in theſe vnited Provinces. God grant that the ſame Navigation may haue a proſperous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding and a fortunate returne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Rome,</hi> the 6. of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>The Perſian Ambaſſadour hath requeſted the Pope that he would giue way to his Maſter, that he might bring in the Greekes Religion into his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And that he would be pleaſed to exhort the Chriſtian Princes to make warre againſt the Turke, to recover the holy Land which the Pope hath promiſed to conſider of, and to returne him an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Naples</hi> are fiue Gallies prepared and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Spaniſh ſouldiers, vnder the Command of <hi>Don Franciſco Mauriques</hi> to ioyne with the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Navie: The Pope hath likewiſe conſented that his Gallies arrived at <hi>Civita Vecchia</hi> from <hi>Naples,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20653:6"/>ſhould ayde the Spaniſh Navie.</p>
               <p>The Councell of State in Spaine, hath conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that ſixe hundred thouſand crownes ſhould be made over for the defence of <hi>Veltolina.</hi> And four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Hollanders haue fought neere <hi>Lifebon,</hi> with nine of the King of Spaines ſhippes, where of they ſunke ſeaven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Venice,</hi> the 12 of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>From <hi>Millaine</hi> we are certified, that the Fort of Saint <hi>Marie</hi> in <hi>Engedin</hi> holdes out as yet, and that eight hundred <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and <hi>Leopoldiſh</hi> Souldiers are come into <hi>Veltoline.</hi> And the King of Spaine was to take his Iourney into Italie. The Ambaſſador of this Seignory, the Lord <hi>Lando,</hi> is lookt for here ſpeedily from England.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Breſlaw,</hi> the 14. of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>The Emperour will ſend three thouſand Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians and other Souldiers into this Countrey to defend the ſame, And will put one thouſand Spaniards in Garriſon for this Citty, but the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens are diſpleaſed with it, where vpon the Duke of <hi>Saxon</hi> will ſend his Garriſons here againe.</p>
               <p>Eight dayes agoe, there happened a great fire at <hi>Poeſen</hi> which burned downe the Cathedrall Church, with two Steeples.</p>
               <p>The Prince of <hi>Poland,</hi> is marched with certaine thouſands towards <hi>Grotra,</hi> to beſiege the Citty of <hi>Riga</hi> and to purſue the <hi>Swedens.</hi> And the King of <hi>Pole</hi> himſelfe in perſon was ſuddenly to follow.</p>
               <p>Yeſterday, was held a generall Muſter, and here paſſed by three hundred Muskets which were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20653:7"/>taken out of the ſtore-houſe of the States of <hi>Sileſia.</hi> And the Imperials intend very ſpeedily with all the force they can to aſſault <hi>Glats.</hi> The young Count of <hi>Thurne</hi> hath rayſed fiue ſconſes before the city, for the defence of it. And a hundred of his forces went a pillaging towards <hi>Frankenbergh</hi> belonging to the Abbot of <hi>Coments,</hi> And ſurpriſing their two troupes of horſe, they ſlue the one, and tooke the other, with the Abbots brother, and a principall Gentleman priſoner, and gott a rich booty, and afterwards they made themſelues Maſters of <hi>Wunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelbergh,</hi> and having pillaged it, went their waies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Vienna,</hi> the 17. of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>The 13. of this month is the Emperour and the Empreſſe received heere in great ſtate and pompe, and the Empreſſe hath beene preſented with many rich gifts, and principally by the Iewes, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto her a ſilver and gilt baſen and Ewer.</p>
               <p>This weeke are ſent againe ſixtie Waggons with munition, and amongſt them ſixe hundred bullets, which waighed 45. pound a peice, going to the ſurpriſe of <hi>Glats,</hi> and there are to follow yet more, and about foure thouſand Souldiers, which the Emperour hath at <hi>Odenburgh</hi> with him, and the Emperour hath ſent the Count of <hi>Harderk</hi> beſides a Secretary of the Court, to the young Count of <hi>Thurne,</hi> to perſwade him to ſurrender the Towne to the Emperour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Prague,</hi> the 18. of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>Laſt Satterday, the Duke of <hi>Lichſtenteene</hi> departed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20653:7"/>from <hi>Vienna,</hi> In the meane time heere are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted certaine Lords to be Deputies in his abſence.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Glats,</hi> wee heare that the Garriſons doe great dammage by pillaging, making their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions as farre as <hi>Brauna,</hi> taking all the booty they can get, and carrying it into the Citty, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſouldiers in the Garriſons of <hi>Moravia</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> haue order given them to march thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to make the ſiege the ſtronger. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Old Count of <hi>Harderk</hi> had order to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the young Count of <hi>Thurne,</hi> to ſurrender the Towne, he could not obtaine it of him, but departed with this anſwere, that he expected aide out of Hungarie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Lipſich</hi> the 21. day of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Saxons</hi> childe is Chriſtened, and the feaſt with great ſtate and pompe ended, and the companie departed with much ioy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
               <p>The Lectorall day appointed at <hi>Regensburgh,</hi> is to bee kept the firſt of <hi>October;</hi> The Elector of <hi>Saxon,</hi> doth purpoſe to come himſelfe in Perſon, if the reſt will doe the like, otherwiſe hee will ſend his Ambaſſadour. And he had rather it had beene kept at <hi>Nurnburgh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Franckfort</hi> the 24. day of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The Magiſtrates of <hi>Franckfort,</hi> conſidering their faire to bee at hand, haue beſought <hi>Monſieur Tilly,</hi> being Generall for the Emperour, and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> that he would giue command to his officers to keepe the wayes cleere, of all Robbers
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20653:8"/>and Theeues; That the Merchants might haue free acceſſe to come and trade there, it being not only beneficiall and neceſſary for the Germane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and the Empire, but likewiſe for the Elector and diuers States of this Empire.</p>
               <p>Whereupon there was the twelfth of this moneth, Pattents publiſhed by the foreſaid <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Tilly</hi> at <hi>Laymen,</hi> where his chiefe quarter is, To all his Generals, Collonels, Captaines, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and other officers, that they ſhall let paſſe, and giue free acceſſe to all Merchants and others, as long as the ſaid <hi>Franckfort Mart</hi> is to laſt, from the nineteenth of <hi>September</hi> enſuing, to the thirtieth, more and aboue eight dayes before the <hi>Mart,</hi> and eight dayes after, to let them paſſe freely and ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with their goods and Merchandize vpon his Highneſſe diſpleaſure and penaltie of their liues.</p>
               <p>Laſt Sunday the <hi>Bavarians</hi> tooke in, <hi>Necker</hi> ground in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and next Munday follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Neckerr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u,</hi> whereupon yeſterday they beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Heidlebergh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſt Munday in the euening, the Arch-Duke <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> with three Companies of ſouldiers, was let into <hi>Wormes,</hi> very willingly by the Cittizens.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Cullen</hi> the 30. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Concerning the beſieging of the Fort called <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penmuts,</hi> there is little or nothing paſt of any conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, for they haue ceaſed of ſhooting into it, vpon the Bergh ſide, becauſe it was to no purpoſe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20653:8"/>but as yet they worke very hard on this ſide, vpon the battery at <hi>Rhynetorpe,</hi> further newes, time will make knowne.</p>
               <p>There arriued certaine hundreths of ſouldiours, in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Halberſtadt,</hi> who did for a time much hurt in that countrey, whereupon Count <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> who keepes his Court at <hi>Weringrata.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Abbeſſe at <hi>Quodlinburgh,</hi> did raiſe in all haſt two thouſand men, whom they carryed into <hi>Halberſtadt,</hi> where the Cittizens ſhut their gates, and ſallyed out vpon them. But when the ſouldiers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated that they might paſſe quietly away, they tooke priſoner their Generall, and Captaines, and Commanders, the reſt were moſt of them deſtroyed and ſcattered, and diuers of them, came to <hi>Mayden-Burgh,</hi> where they reported, that they will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſtronger then they were, and fetch their pay.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Berghen</hi> vp <hi>Zome</hi> the 2. of <hi>September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We heare that of late, the 29. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> being Munday in the euening, the enemy made another great aſſault vpon the trenches, but they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beaten off againe, with the loſſe of about ſome fiue hundred men, being for the moſt part al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all Spaniards, In the meane time they ſhort with their Cannon very fiercely into the Towne through certaine houſes and Turrets, yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great hurt, ſo that hitherto they haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed but little; Moreouer, they fell vpon the out-workes in three ſeverall places withall their power, ſo that the fight continued from fiue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20653:9"/>of the clocke in the euening, vntill midnight, ſo that many chiefe Spaniards and men of worth were ſlaine. And they within the Towne got a rich boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and although the enemy doth ſtriue to get neere the hauen, yet is he mette withall, from the new-workes, ſo that there is no doubt, he will likewiſe little prevaile on that ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Emmericke.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Count <hi>Henry Vandenbergh,</hi> lyeth as yet at a towne called <hi>Goch,</hi> and few dayes agoe, he had almoſt his whole Armie brought vpon the Cleviſh heath all in Armour, to what intent, is as yet vnknowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Nannow</hi> the 22. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We heare for certaine, that <hi>Spiers</hi> and <hi>Wormes</hi> are both taken in by <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> who hath altered the Gouernance, and diſaſured the Burges, that <hi>Heidle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> is beſieged and battered; that they cannot long hold out, <hi>Frankendale</hi> is beſieged alſo, and none can goe out or in, but as yet not battered. Their remaines no more but <hi>Mainchem</hi> and <hi>Denſbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough</hi> vnbeſieged, all which is done by the forces of <hi>Leopoldus</hi> and <hi>Banaſia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From the <hi>Hage</hi> the 4. of <hi>September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>We heare now for certaine from <hi>Breda,</hi> that <hi>Manſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> arriued at a place, called <hi>Oſterwick,</hi> in the Lant-ſtate neere <hi>Breda,</hi> within a mile or two at the moſt, where they are lodged to refreſh themſelues, hauing muſtered 10000 horſe, and 4000. foote, in his paſſage, it is thought he hath
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20653:9"/>loſt no leſſe than 4000. Horſe and Foot: <hi>Gonſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los de Cordua</hi> (as it is vpon the beſt intelligence certified) hath not loſt of his owne and the countrey Bores leſſe then 12. or 13. thouſand in ſeuerall encounters with <hi>Mansfield,</hi> in his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage thorow <hi>Henault Liege,</hi> and <hi>Brabant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From <hi>Breda</hi> we likewiſe vnderſtand for certaine that ſince <hi>Cordua</hi> his comming to <hi>Spinola</hi> his Campe, they haue made ſeuerall fierce aſſaults vpon the Towne of <hi>Bergen-vpzom,</hi> and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the firſt of September <hi>Spinola</hi> (after he had beene repulſed at a halfe Moone in one of the out workes of the Towne aſſailed certaine new workes lying towards <hi>Breda,</hi> twixt two Forts of the Towne, with certaine <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>Walloun</hi> Companies of D. <hi>Cordua:</hi> the which workes were kept by a <hi>Walloun</hi> Commander and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Wallouns,</hi> and for a long time valiantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, but being ouer furiouſly charged by D. <hi>Corduas</hi> Souldiers, was ſurpriſed and taken.</p>
               <p>In the meane time comes Coronell <hi>Morgan</hi> with certaine Companies of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of his Regiment, and certaine Companies of <hi>Scots</hi> of Coronell <hi>Henderſons</hi> Regiment lately deceaſed, (which Regiment of <hi>Scots</hi> are ſince vnder the Command of Sir <hi>Francis Henderſon</hi> being Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronell in his brothers place) and ſeconds the <hi>Wallouns</hi> with ſuch reſolution and courage, that they put them all to the ſword, and poſſeſt the workes againe; In which conflict they killed dead in the place 800. of D. <hi>Corduas</hi> men, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20653:10"/>got great booty by the rifling of their dead men. Since which time (leauing his former courſe of ſurpriſing by furious aſſaults) he hath begunne another manner of way to gaine the ſame, (and hath vowed either to take it within a ſhort ſpace of Michaelmaſſe next, or elſe to loſe his whole Armie) by plying 40. Canons againſt the ſame to batter it downe to the ground; but how ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily he can doe the ſame, time will ſhew.</p>
               <p>Further wee vnderſtand from <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſent a Trumpetter to her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to deſire that all priſoners taken may be rendered or ranſommed, according to the law of Armes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From Conſtantinople.</head>
               <p>SInce the late relation of <hi>Turkey</hi> ſent by Sir <hi>Thomas Roe,</hi> It is written that there is fallen out a great diuiſion betwixt the <hi>Spahies,</hi> which are certaine horſemen, and the <hi>Ianiſaries,</hi> the <hi>Ianiſaries</hi> fauouring the preſent Emperour, the <hi>Spahies</hi> fauouring the elder Brother of the late Sultan <hi>Oſman,</hi> and doe labour to ſet him in the Throne, and to diſplace <hi>Muſtapha</hi> the preſent Emperour; ſo that in the Citie of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> by reaſon of theſe Ciuill diſſentions, it is very dangerous for all Strangers to make their abode there.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe reported, that the <hi>Basſhawes</hi> in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20653:10"/>ſeuerall countries are gathering together forces, each one to ſtrengthen themſelues, ſeeking op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity euery man to poſſeſſe his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie as principall Lord, as it fell out after the death of <hi>Alexander</hi> the great amongſt his twelue Commanders, which poſſeſſed euerie man for themſelues, and ſo ceaſed the vniuerſall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narke of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <head>From <hi>Rome</hi> the 26. of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Pope hauing beene lately very ſicke, is recouered againe; for the which there haue beene great Proceſſions, and ſinging <hi>Te Deum laudamus.</hi> His Holineſſe being highly offended with the Gouernour of <hi>Naples,</hi> for detaining of his Gallies ſo long; and the great Princeſſe which hee expected ſhould haue beene eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to one of his Nephewes: whereupon hee hath commanded the ſaid Viceroy of <hi>Naples</hi> to make his appearance at <hi>Rome,</hi> and craue pardon, but he refuſeth the ſame in regard of his place; and being the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Subiect, he cannot doe the ſame without his leaue, ſo that it is thought there will grow ſome diſcontent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Pope and the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the rather, for that this Pope was choſen without the conſent of any of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cardinalls.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="account">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20653:11"/>
               <head>From the <hi>Hage</hi> the 10. of <hi>September.</hi> Stilo Nouo.</head>
               <p>IT is written that thoſe of the Towne of <hi>Berg,</hi> haue this weeke made an aſſault vpon a ſconce or Fort of the Enemies called the Cat. (The ſaid Fort being planted with many Ordnance did more offend the towne then any worke beſides) which was ſo valiantly aſſailed, that they tooke it in, and brought their Ordnance into the towne, raiſed the Fort, and made it leuill with the ground, in which ſeruice there was ſlaine many men on both ſides: But of the certaine truth, and of the more particular manner thereof you ſhall vnderſtand more by the next Poſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Copie of a Letter receiued from <hi>Vtrech,</hi> this preſent 13. of <hi>September.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIr, I haue no newes to write to you at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent but this; The Noble <hi>Haſtroke, Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwicks</hi> Brother, had his arme cut off in two places, to the generall griefe of the true hearted. It is alſo credibly reported (with vs) that <hi>Heidle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge, Manhem</hi> and <hi>Frankendale,</hi> ate all at once beleiger'd, ſo that the poore <hi>Palatinate</hi> has not in all his natiue Country one ſimple Harbor to ſhelter himſelfe in, nor one piece of ground in command whereon to ſet his foote.</p>
               <p>There is a generall faſt to be obſerued in all the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20653:11"/>vnited Prouinces, the 10. of <hi>September,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the new ſtile, ſo that we doe expect ſome great matters to be done ſuddenly, the Count of <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath well refreſhed his men, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth them dayly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o that there is in the field vnder his command about 16. thouſand braue Souldiers, Horſe and Foote, and it is hoped ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the paſſages to <hi>Spinola</hi> his Campe will be more and more ſtreightned, which he fearing doth with the more violence aſſault the towne dayly.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Middleborough</hi> is aduiſed that the 60. men of warre of the States, which are waiting vpon the Weſt India ſiluer and gold Fleete, haue taken 12. Spaniſh ſhips, comming from <hi>Braſilia,</hi> very rich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> laden, and are thought to be worth at leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound ſterling.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>mes newes from <hi>Alepo,</hi> that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>llanders haue taken <hi>Ormus</hi> from the Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, being a City of great importance, and of great trafficke, lying vpon the borders of <hi>Perſia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>From <hi>Spinolaes</hi> Campe, lying before <hi>Berghen vpzom</hi> the 2. of <hi>September.</hi> A Letter <hi>printed at</hi> Antwerpe.</head>
               <p>IT is reported by a Gentleman that came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long all the way in Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> Army, from <hi>Sedan</hi> to <hi>Gemblours,</hi> where the battell was fought betweene him and <hi>Gonzales,</hi> that there were ſome 2000. of his Horſe that did mutine
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20653:12"/>againſt him, thinking that it was not likely or poſſible for him with his Army that way to paſſe that he then intended, and is now paſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo ſtrong oppoſition. Thoſe neuer gaue a ſtroke in the battell, and if they had fought as the reſt of <hi>Mansfields</hi> forces did, <hi>Don Gonzaloes</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had bin (as is very likely) quite ouerthrowne.</p>
               <p>We got newes the 30. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> that Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Halberſtadt,</hi> loſt in the a foreſaid fight aboue 2000. men. Wherefore vpon the ſame and the next day in the euening, we made here great ſhewes of mirth, making of Bon-fires, diſcharging of our ordnance, the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiteres gaue likewiſe 3. volies with their ſhot, and thoſe which carried Pikes, put bundles of ſtraw on them, and went ſo with them aloft, to ſpite the Enemy, it ſeemeth that our who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> was ſet on fire, and the Pipes, Drums, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets were euery where brauely ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſame was likewiſe done the next day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>The Garriſon within <hi>Berghen</hi> was in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> meane time very quiet, but the next day, hauing vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> was ſafely arriued at <hi>Breda,</hi> with 14000. horſe and foots, and that he hauing ſlaine 3000. of <hi>Gonzaloes</hi> foreces, had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the field, &amp; taken diuers of his pieces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance beſides his money and bagage, they began likewiſe to make ſignes of ioy, and diſcharged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance both of great and ſmall ſhot, &amp; in the euening they made exceeding great bon-fires, reioycing mightily in regard of the arriuall of their much expected friends, Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20653:12"/>and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> who as they hoped ſhould be their redeemer, and free them from their enemies.</p>
               <p>By this precedent Relation or Letter, you may perceiue what <hi>Mansfields</hi> very enemies doe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of his late battel, which ſome here in <hi>England</hi> tranſported with affection, will not beleeue but that he had the worſt of it, nay that he was vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defeated.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>The Printers Aduertiſemnet.</head>
            <p>THere was printed the 9. of this month a Relation or booke of newes, wherein were foiſted in (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Licencers knowledge) certaine fabulous paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ely that Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſhould haue in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>00. women or whores, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> only falſe but alſo ſcandalous, to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Neighbours and friends, which may pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>caſion ſome to thinke the weekely Cun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ſſed without any care or regard what is print<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> publiſhed (as formerly when things were d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>out order) but I will aſſure you the contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>atſoeuer is licenſed is throughly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>nted according to the high or low Duch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>opies, or out of Letters of the beſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>d the Seas, and that whoſoeuer hath or ſhall ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>, or put any thing more then hath beene iudiciouſly examined and approued, is liable to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely puniſhed: therefore expect no ſuch bold at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt from any of vs hereafter. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
